<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on In Data We Trust</title>
    <link>/categories/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on In Data We Trust</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducing iDEP analyses with auto-generated R Markdown</title>
      <link>/post/reproducing-idep-analyses-with-auto-generated-r-markdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/reproducing-idep-analyses-with-auto-generated-r-markdown/</guid>
      <description>This R markdown file was auto-generated by iDEP, a tool for interactive analysis of RNA-Seq data. It is assumed that users have analyzed their data with iDEP by clicking through all the tabs and have downloaded the related files to a folder.
1. Read data R packages and iDEP core Functions. Users can also download the iDEP_core_functions.R file. Many R packages needs to be installed first. This may take hours.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blogdown notes</title>
      <link>/post/blogdown-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/blogdown-notes/</guid>
      <description>This website is created using RStudio following this tutorial with tips from Ming Tang.
To start a new post, choose &amp;ldquo;New post&amp;rdquo; from Addins. Use Markdown for texts. Use RMarkdown if it contains R markdown to render plots, etc.
Choose which files you want to work on from the right bottom window. Save the files changed and the webpage is rendered automatically in the Viewer window.
To disable a widget, change the header from active=true to active=false</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DESeq2 experimental design and interpretation</title>
      <link>/post/deseq2-experimental-design-and-interpretation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/deseq2-experimental-design-and-interpretation/</guid>
      <description>Update. 11/13/17 Thanks to Mike Love for pointing out an error. This is just my understanding. There maybe other errors.
To allow complex study designs in iDEP(http://ge-lab.org/idep/), I tried to understand how factoral models are built and the desired results are extracted from DESeq2. The following is based on the help document from the resutls( ) function in DESeq2, plus some of Mike Love&amp;rsquo;s answers to questions from users.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>